LIKE FLOWERS IN SAND
LIKE FLOWERS IN SAND
Kim Baek-du, did you find it? Come on and bring it here.
Kim Baek-du, kau menemukannya? Cepat bawa kemari.
Okay.
Baiklah.
Come on.
Ayolah.
Hurry!
Cepatlah!
FIRST GEUMGANG-CLASS CHAMPIONSHIP
KEJUARAAN KELAS GEUMGANG PERTAMA
24-HOUR SCENE
TKP 24 JAM
Hey, it's starting now.
Sudah dimulai.
We received reports
Kami menerima laporan
of rampant pickpocketing around the subway station
soal maraknya pencopetan di stasiun kereta bawah tanah
and went to investigate in hopes of gathering information.
dan pergi menyelidikinya dengan harapan mendapatkan informasi.
Most pickpockets' eyes
Kebanyakan mata pencopet
are fixed on people's belongings
terfokus pada barang-barang
such as handbags, rather than people.
seperti tas, alih-alih orang.
KIM GEUM-GANG FIRST GEUMGANG-CLASS CHAMPIONSHIP
KIM GEUM-GANG KEJUARAAN KELAS GEUMGANG PERTAMA
EPISODE 4 I KNOW WHAT YOU DID THAT DAY
EPISODE 4 AKU TAHU PERBUATANMU HARI ITU
I didn't say anything wrong.
Aku tak salah ucap.
I can say that much because she's married.
Aku bicara begitu karena dia sudah menikah.
And why is she still so violent? Jeez.
Kenapa dia masih saja begitu kasar? Astaga.
Darn it.
Sialan.
And she's been lying to me, saying that she wasn't Du-sik.
Dia bohong kepadaku dengan mengaku dia bukan Du-sik.
What about that?
Apa maksudnya?
Why are you so surprised? As if you didn't know.
Kenapa begitu terkejut? Seolah-olah kau tak tahu.
Hey.
Hei.
-Oh Du-sik, you… -Baek-du.
- Oh Du-sik, kau… - Baek-du.
No matter how hard you try, I can see right through you.
Sekeras apa pun kau berusaha, aku ini mengenalmu.
So stop saying you hate ssireum. You don't even mean it.
Berhenti bilang kau benci ssireum. Kau tak bersungguh-sungguh.
Come back while I ask nicely.
Kembalilah selagi kuminta baik-baik.
Du-sik, look.
Du-sik, dengar.
-Why are you doing this to me-- -Because I need you.
- Kenapa kau lakukan… - Aku butuh kau.
Both the team and I need you.
Aku dan tim sama-sama membutuhkanmu.
We need you, Baek-du.
Kami butuh kau, Baek-du.
I…
Aku…
really need you to be here.
sangat butuh kau di sini.
Well, but…
Namun…
Is this okay?
Apa tidak apa-apa?
What do you mean?
Apa maksudmu?
I mean, you…
Maksudku, kau…
You're married.
Kau sudah menikah.
And?
Lalu?
Well, since you're married now
Karena kau sudah menikah
and have a husband,
dan punya suami,
maybe you're not supposed to say
mungkin tak seharusnya kau mengatakan
things like that to me.
hal seperti itu kepadaku.
Okay. Keep going.
Baiklah. Teruskan.
Don't put me in a bind.
Jangan mempersulitku.
Wait, what are you thinking?
Tunggu, apa yang kau pikirkan?
Me and you?
Aku dan kau?
Kim Baek-du!
Kim Baek-du!
Have you lost your mind?
Kau sudah gila?
-That hurts. -Stay away from me.
- Aduh. - Menjauhlah dariku.
-Or I'll kill you. -Wait, Du-sik.
- Atau kubunuh kau. - Tunggu, Du-sik.
If you come near me, I'll throw you.
Jika mendekat, akan kulempar.
-Wait. -Got it?
- Tunggu. - Paham?
-Hey. -You must be crazy.
- Hei. - Kau pasti sudah gila.
-Wait. -I can't believe this.
- Tunggu. - Sulit dipercaya.
Wait a moment. You…
Tunggu sebentar. Kau…
-What's the matter? -Be quiet.
- Ada apa? - Diamlah.
Why?
Kenapa?
What is it? Du-sik!
Kenapa? Du-sik!
If that's not what it is, why would she need me?
Jika bukan itu, kenapa dia butuh aku?
And why would she look at me like that?
Dan kenapa dia menatapku seperti itu?
Kim Baek-du must have completely lost his mind.
Kim Baek-du pasti sudah gila.
I mean, what does he take me for?
Maksudku, dia anggap aku apa?
That is the most ridiculous thing I've ever heard in my life.
Itu hal terkonyol yang kudengar seumur hidupku.
That was insulting.
Itu penghinaan.
And absolutely humiliating.
Dan sangat merendahkan.
What?
Apa?
Honey.
Sayang.
Could you please stop calling me "honey"?
Bisa berhenti panggil "sayang"?
Ms. Chu.
Bu Chu.
-What does that mean? -Ms. Chu is here.
- Apa maksudmu? - Bu Chu datang.
Too late to put on a show.
Percuma saja berakting.
I heard you arguing out there.
Aku tadi dengar kalian bertengkar.
Is this really your best?
Hanya ini kemampuan kalian?
Captain, what are you doing here?
Kapten, sedang apa di sini?
Why?
Kenapa?
-I'm not allowed to come here? -That's not it.
- Aku tak boleh kemari? - Bukan begitu.
This tastes bad.
Rasanya tak enak.
On the day Choi died, he had a fight with someone.
Pada hari kematian Choi, dia bertengkar dengan seseorang.
A CCTV here caught it.
CCTV di sini merekamnya.
Mom, did you hear?
Ibu, dengar itu?
The new general manager of the ssireum team recommended
Manajer umum baru tim ssireum merekomendasikan
Baek-du as the new coach.
Baek-du sebagai pelatih baru.
CONGRATULATIONS ON RETIREMENT
SELAMAT ATAS PENSIUNNYA
What's there to hesitate about?
Apa yang perlu dipertimbangkan?
This is a rare opportunity, you know.
Ini kesempatan langka.
But it's kind of awkward.
Tapi itu agak canggung.
What's so awkward? Just suck it up and do it.
Apanya yang canggung? Terima dan jalanilah.
Jin-su…
Jin-su…
I'm putting him in a somewhat awkward position now.
Aku kini menempatkannya di posisi canggung.
He even turned down the other coaching position to come here.
Dia menolak posisi kepelatihan lain agar bisa ke sini.
Goodness, our baby brother has such a kind heart,
Astaga, adik kecil kita baik sekali,
worrying about four-time champion Jin-su.
mencemaskan Jin-su yang empat kali juara.
You're definitely going to heaven.
Kau akan masuk surga.
Seriously, you better worry about yourself.
Astaga, sebaiknya kau khawatirkan dirimu.
Did you see Jin-su's car?
Kau lihat mobil Jin-su?
His car costs more than your salary.
Harga mobilnya lebih mahal dari gajimu.
Who are you to talk?
Kau sendiri?
It's not just about Jin-su.
Ini bukan hanya soal Jin-su.
How can I be a coach when I've never won a championship?
Bagaimana bisa menjadi pelatih jika tak pernah juara?
I told you. It doesn't matter.
Sudah kubilang, itu tak penting.
God, you're so frustrating.
Kau sungguh mengesalkan.
Look.
Dengar.
Father won numerous championships,
Ayah memenangkan banyak kejuaraan,
but he's horrible at teaching.
tapi dia payah dalam melatih.
The ability to convey information and help others understand.
Kemampuan menyampaikan informasi dan membantu orang lain memahaminya.
Hey, what's it called? Making others understand things.
Hei, apa sebutannya? Membuat orang mengerti.
Teaching. Father can't teach.
Mengajar. Ayah tak bisa itu.
Right. Teaching. Teacher.
Benar. Mengejar. Guru.
-"Ching"? -Yes, that.
- "Mengajar"? - Ya, itu.
Anyhow, just act cool and accept the job.
Intinya, bersikaplah keren dan terima pekerjaan itu.
This is a great chance!
Ini kesempatan besar!
Gosh, enough already.
Astaga, sudahlah.
Stop trying to convince me. I made up my mind. Just stop it.
Berhenti meyakinkanku. Aku sudah membuat keputusan. Hentikan.
You're going to freeze and starve!
Kau akan kedinginan dan kelaparan!
Hey!
Hei!
Jeez, what do I do with that clueless punk?
Aku harus apa dengan anak bodoh itu?
Just leave him alone.
Biarkan saja dia.
If it doesn't work out, I can start livestreaming with him.
Jika itu tak berhasil, aku bisa siaran dengannya.
How strange.
Aneh sekali.
Where did it go?
Ke mana perginya?
Everything else is here except that one.
Semua ada kecuali yang itu.
What are you looking for?
Kau mencari apa?
You know the tape from when you won the championship for the first time?
Kau tahu kaset saat kau menang kejuaraan untuk kali pertama?
-I want to review that. -Okay.
- Aku ingin mengulasnya. - Baiklah.
But that's the only tape that's missing.
Tapi hanya kaset itu yang hilang.
-Did you take it? -No, I don't know where it is.
- Kau mengambilnya? - Tidak, aku tidak tahu di mana.
Baek-du!
Baek-du!
How strange.
Aneh sekali.
There's one thing I don't quite understand.
Ada satu hal yang tidak bisa kupahami.
Why did Choi Chil-seong come out to the boondocks with an APB out on him?
Kenapa Choi Chil-seong pergi ke perdesaan padahal masuk dalam DPO?
If I were him, I would've fled overseas with the money and lay low.
Jika menjadi dia, aku kabur ke luar negeri dengan uangnya dan sembunyi.
Old habits die hard. He was probably trying to score some cash here.
Kebiasaan lama sulit hilang. Dia mungkin ingin dapat uang di sini.
From a ssireum game in the boonies? After all the big games?
Dari laga ssireum di perdesaan? Setelah semua laga besar itu?
He would've been too proud for that.
Dia akan terlalu gengsi.
And besides, Choi Chil-seong is dead now.
Selain itu, kini Choi Chil-seong sudah tiada.
-So-- -Then go.
- Jadi… - Kalau begitu, pergilah.
I didn't ask you to follow me here.
Aku tak memintamu ikut kemari.
You think I wanted to come here?
Pikirmu aku mau datang kemari?
I'm here because Captain told me to come.
Aku datang karena Kapten memintaku.
What a loving family.
Sungguh keluarga yang harmonis.
Hey.
Hei.
How long do you think you can hold out here like this?
Kalian pikir berapa lama bisa bertahan di sini seperti ini?
Just pack up then.
Kalau begitu, berkemaslah.
And come with me when I head back to Seoul later.
Ikut denganku kembali ke Seoul nanti.
So what's your point?
Jadi, apa maksudmu?
What do you want to do?
Apa yang kau ingin lakukan?
I don't think it's too late
Kurasa belum terlambat
-to publicize the investigation-- -No.
- memublikasikan penyelidikan… - Tidak.
Because we need to find out why Choi came to Geosan, whom he met,
Kita harus tahu alasan Choi datang ke Geosan, bertemu siapa,
and who killed him.
dan siapa pembunuhnya.
Yu-gyeong, are you sure about this?
Yu-gyeong, kau yakin soal ini?
You're certain you can uncover all that?
Kau yakin bisa mengungkap semua itu?
Yes.
Ya.
Is that so?
Begitukah?
-Then give it a go. -Captain.
- Maka cobalah. - Kapten.
You can't stay undercover for long anyway.
Kalian juga tak bisa lama menyamar.
So either find Choi's ledger or the murder suspect as soon as possible.
Jadi, segera temukan buku besar Choi atau tersangka pembunuhnya.
Understood?
Mengerti?
This is all because of Oh Du-sik.
Ini semua karena Oh Du-sik.
Now, I'm in a pickle.
Kini, aku dalam masalah.
She's definitely trying to screw me over.
Dia jelas ingin menghancurkanku.
She must've had all this planned out and…
Dia pasti sudah merencanakan ini dan…
That lady…
Wanita itu…
The smoke ring?
Lingkaran asap?
But what's she doing here?
Sedang apa dia di sini?
He actually made a fair point.
Sesungguhnya dia ada benarnya.
If you don't find anything soon, I'll call you back.
Jika tak segera dapat informasi, kuhubungi kalian lagi.
Okay.
Baiklah.
And you, keep an eye on her. If she loses it again, call me right away.
Dan kau, terus awasi dia. Jika dia lepas kendali lagi, hubungi aku.
Yes, ma'am.
Baik, Bu.
You guys.
Kalian.
You're not arguing every day, are you?
Jangan bertengkar setiap hari, ya?
-No, ma'am.
- Baik, Bu.
You better behave. I'll be keeping an eye on you.
Sebaiknya kalian jaga sikap. Aku akan mengawasi kalian.
You guys make me so worried.
Kalian membuatku sangat khawatir.
Don't follow me. You'll only give me a headache.
Jangan ikuti aku. Kalian hanya membuatku sakit kepala.
-Yes, ma'am. -Have a safe trip back.
- Baik, Bu. - Hati-hati di jalan pulang.
Go now.
Pergilah.
You fool.
Dasar bodoh.
Why do you let her walk all over you like that?
Kenapa mau diperlakukan seperti itu?
Can you believe it?
Bisa kau percaya?
This is just ridiculous!
Ini tak masuk akal!
Now, my boy Jin-su has nowhere to go.
Sekarang tak ada tempat bagi Jin-su, putraku.
This is a funny situation indeed.
Ini memang situasi konyol.
But Jin-su shouldn't have come
Namun, Jin-su seharusnya tidak datang
just after that one talk with Head Coach Park.
hanya setelah sekali bicara dengan Pelatih Kepala Park.
-He should've signed the contract-- -What?
- Seharusnya dia tanda tangani kontrak… - Apa?
Hey, look.
Hei, dengar.
How would he have known things would turn out this way?
Bagaimana kami bisa tahu semuanya akan seperti ini?
He came because Head Coach Park begged him to.
Dia datang karena Pelatih Kepala Park memohon kepadanya.
Jin-su didn't do anything wrong, except for being tender-hearted!
Jin-su tak berbuat salah, selain punya hati yang sangat baik!
I didn't say he did something wrong.
Aku tak bilang dia salah.
I'm just saying, if Jin-su can't be the coach--
Maksudku, andai Jin-su tak bisa jadi pelatih…
Why can't he? Why?
Kenapa tak bisa? Kenapa?
He's obviously better than Baek-du in every aspect! So why?
Jelas dia lebih baik dari Baek-du dalam berbagai aspek! Lantas kenapa?
Why would you say that?
Kenapa kau berkata begitu?
That's why I said, "if."
Itulah sebabnya kubilang "andai".
Jeez, just forget it. Now I'm too scared to say anything.
Astaga, lupakan. Kini aku terlalu takut untuk bicara.
Why Baek-du, of all people?
Kenapa harus Baek-du?
I'm not eating this.
Aku tak mau makan ini.
-Sit down! -Fine. Darn it.
- Duduk! - Baiklah. Sial.
-Hello. -Hey.
- Halo. - Hei.
What a weird situation, right?
Ini situasi yang aneh, 'kan?
Shall we talk inside? Come in.
Mau bicara di dalam? Masuklah.
Let's go.
Ayo.
Our manager didn't say anything before.
Sebelumnya, manajer kami tak mengatakan apa pun.
Then suddenly, yesterday, Baek-du's name came up.
Lalu kemarin, tiba-tiba nama Baek-du disebutkan.
-Have a seat. -Okay.
- Duduklah. - Baik.
Gosh. Why couldn't it have come up sooner?
Astaga. Kenapa tak disebutkan sejak awal?
Before I called you here.
Sebelum aku meneleponmu kemari.
A new general manager?
Ada manajer umum baru?
What? Yes.
Apa? Ya.
A new manager, recently hired by the governor.
Manajer baru yang direkrut gubernur.
The governor?
Gubernur?
Were they recruited from some other team?
Mereka direkrut dari tim lain?
No idea. Maybe somebody asked him for a favor.
Entahlah. Mungkin seseorang meminta bantuannya.
But the manager seemed to be quite good at ssireum.
Tapi sepertinya manajer itu cukup andal dalam ssireum.
On the first day, one of the boys got on her nerves,
Pada hari pertama, salah satu anggota membuatnya kesal
and she threw him right over.
dan dia membantingnya.
What? What's the manager's name?
Apa? Siapa nama manajer itu?
Yu-gyeong. Oh Yu-gyeong.
Yu-gyeong. Oh Yu-gyeong.
-So a woman? -Yeah.
- Jadi, dia perempuan? - Ya.
The governor requested multiple times
Gubernur meminta beberapa kali
that we cooperate with her.
agar kami bekerja sama dengannya.
So I can't just disregard her opinion.
Jadi, aku tak bisa abaikan opininya.
I'll see if I can convince the manager.
Akan kucoba meyakinkan manajer itu.
Just give me a few days, okay?
Beri aku beberapa hari, ya?
Don't say "hi-yah." They know what it is.
Jangan bilang "hi-yah". Mereka tahu apa itu.
Your form is a bit…
Posturmu agak…
Sorry?
Apa?
When you use that technique, you shouldn't pull the satba down.
Saat memakai teknik itu, kau tak boleh menarik turun satba.
Leaning backwards will make it easier to throw him.
Condong ke belakang akan mempermudah melemparnya.
Well… Actually,
Soal itu… Sebenarnya,
Baek-du told me to do it this way the other day.
Baek-du memberitahuku untuk melakukannya seperti ini tempo hari.
Should I try again?
Haruskah kucoba lagi?
No. Whatever is more comfortable for you.
Tidak. Lakukan yang lebih nyaman untukmu.
Keep it up.
Teruskanlah.
Hey.
Hei.
The top student says the answer is number three
Murid terbaik bilang jawabannya nomor tiga
and a so-so one says it's number five, and you're picking number five?
dan yang biasa saja bilang nomor lima, tapi kau pilih nomor lima?
Use your brain, will you?
Gunakanlah otakmu.
Stop. That's enough.
Hentikan. Sudah cukup.
-Let's get back to practice. -Come on.
- Mari kembali berlatih. - Ayo.
Hello.
Halo.
A new general manager?
Ada manajer umum baru?
Yes. A new manager, recently hired by the governor.
Ya. Manajer baru yang direkrut gubernur.
Jeez.
Astaga.
That punk has such creepy eyes.
Mata berandal itu mengerikan.
KIM BAEK-DU
KIM BAEK-DU
Come to our spot after work.
Ke tempat kita saat pulang.
What is this now?
Apa lagi sekarang?
Wow.
Hebat.
Was this place always this small?
Tempatnya memang sekecil ini?
From what I remember, I had to run
Seingatku, aku harus berlari
for quite a while to get there from this end.
cukup jauh agar tiba di sana dari ujung sini.
What are you saying?
Apa maksudmu?
Even back then, you could run from here to there in no time.
Bahkan dahulu, kau bisa cepat berlari dari sini ke sana.
Will you be quiet?
Bisakah kau diam?
I'm having a moment here.
Aku sedang menikmati momen.
Does that taste good, by the way?
Omong-omong, apakah itu rasanya enak?
This?
Ini?
-Would you like a sip? -No, I can't drink.
- Kau mau seteguk? - Tidak, aku tak bisa minum alkohol.
You can't drink? Why?
Kau tak bisa minum? Kenapa?
Are you sick?
Kau sakit?
Sick? No way! I'm very healthy.
Sakit? Tidak! Aku sangat sehat.
And energetic.
Dan penuh energi.
I think my body just can't take alcohol.
Kurasa tubuhku tak bisa menerima alkohol.
Whenever I drink, I can't remember anything later.
Tiap kali minum alkohol, nantinya aku tak bisa ingat apa pun.
Jeez. Can you be more pathetic?
Astaga. Kau ini sangat menyedihkan, ya?
What? What is it?
Kenapa? Ada apa?
Why do you keep looking at me like that?
Kenapa terus melihatku seperti itu?
No reason.
Tidak ada alasan.
You really have a knack of getting on my nerves.
Kau sungguh mudah membuatku jengkel.
Do you know that?
Kau tahu itu?
Be careful.
Hati-hati.
That's not it.
Bukan begitu.
I saw it.
Aku melihatnya.
I saw everything earlier.
Aku melihat semuanya tadi.
Saw what?
Melihat apa?
You being scolded by some lady in front of your house.
Kau dimarahi seorang wanita di depan rumahmu.
Hey.
Hei.
Is she who I'm thinking?
Apa dia seperti dugaanku?
Is she?
Begitukah?
What do you mean?
Apa maksudmu?
She's your mother-in-law.
Dia ibu mertuamu.
By the way, she looked familiar.
Omong-omong, dia tampak tak asing.
I think I've seen her on a TV show.
Kurasa aku pernah melihatnya di acara televisi.
-What TV show? -You know…
- Acara televisi apa? - Kau tahu…
The…
Soal…
Right. Love and War.
Aku ingat. Love and War.
That's right. Love and War.
Benar. Love and War.
Oh, I see.
Begitu rupanya.
From what I saw earlier,
Dari yang kulihat tadi,
she didn't seem any different from the ladies on that show.
dia tak tampak berbeda dari wanita di acara itu.
You think?
Menurutmu begitu?
Does she nag you a lot?
Dia sering memarahimu?
Basically every time she sees me.
Bisa dibilang setiap kali dia melihatku.
What does your husband do? He was just staying in the back earlier.
Apa yang suamimu lakukan? Dia hanya berdiri di belakang tadi.
Oh, him.
Dia.
He doesn't know anything. He's still too young.
Dia tak tahu apa pun. Dia masih terlalu muda.
He's young? How old is he?
Dia masih muda? Berapa usianya?
He must be 32.
Usianya pasti 32 tahun.
No, he's 33.
Tidak, dia 33 tahun.
That's not young. He's all grown up.
Itu bukan muda. Dia sudah dewasa.
What kind of husband does that?
Suami macam apa yang melakukan itu?
What's with you? Why do you look so upset?
Ada apa denganmu? Kenapa kau terlihat sangat kesal?
Sometimes, I talk back to her pretty strongly too. You know my temper.
Terkadang, aku juga menjawabnya cukup ketus. Kau tahu kepribadianku.
But still.
Tapi tetap saja.
You should've been careful before marrying him.
Seharusnya kau hati-hati sebelum menikah.
It's not that bad. You don't have to worry about it.
Tidak seburuk itu. Kau tak perlu mencemaskannya.
About what you said to me the other day…
Soal perkataanmu kepadaku tempo hari…
What?
Apa?
You told me to go back to the ssireum team.
Kau memintaku kembali ke tim ssireum.
Right.
Benar.
About that,
Soal itu,
I'll think about it carefully.
aku akan memikirkannya baik-baik.
It's not like Jin-su won the championships by Ghost Leg.
Jin-su bukan menang kejuaraan secara diundi.
He won them because he was so good.
Dia menang karena sangat hebat.
So he should be the coach.
Dia seharusnya jadi pelatih.
-Right. -Makes sense.
- Ya. - Itu logis.
I get your point,
Aku paham maksudmu,
but being good at something
tapi hebat dalam sesuatu
doesn't mean that you're good at teaching it.
bukan berarti kau pandai dalam mengajarinya.
I mean, take my daughter's tutor, for example.
Maksudku, lihat saja tutor putriku, sebagai contohnya.
She went to the best university, but was worthless at teaching.
Dia masuk kampus terbaik, tapi tak pandai mengajar.
"Why can't you understand this?"
"Kenapa kau tak bisa memahami ini?"
"Why doesn't she understand this, ma'am?"
"Kenapa dia tak memahami ini, Bu?"
Come on. Jin-su won't be like that.
Ayolah. Jin-su tak akan seperti itu.
-Right. -Well, I don't think
- Benar. - Kurasa
Jin-su gets along very well with his juniors.
Jin-su tak akrab dengan para juniornya.
But these boys love Baek-du.
Tapi mereka menyukai Baek-du.
-Right. -But Jin-su is just so cold.
- Benar. - Jin-su memang tak berekspresi.
It's not some social gathering, you know.
Itu bukan perkumpulan sosial.
A coach must have good ssireum skills.
Pelatih harus punya keahlian ssireum.
But…
Tapi…
-Baek-du isn't that bad at ssireum either. -That's right.
- Baek-du juga cukup hebat dalam ssireum. - Benar.
He just never got to show all the skills he has.
Dia hanya belum pernah bisa menunjukkan keterampilannya.
Come on. That means he's just bad at it.
Ayolah. Itu artinya dia payah.
He's just bad.
Dia memang payah.
Wait. Keep it down.
Tunggu. Pelankan suaramu.
What's up?
Ada apa?
-Hey. -What?
- Hei. - Apa?
-Oh, no. -This is bad.
- Astaga. - Ini gawat.
Oh, no. What do we do?
Astaga. Bagaimana ini?
Oh, dear.
Astaga.
We must choose, one way or another. We can't live like this forever.
Kita harus pilih salah satunya. Tak bisa hidup begini selamanya.
Jin-su's mom won't even give you extra side dishes
Ibu Jin-su bahkan tak memberimu tambahan lauk
if you say you support Baek-du.
jika kau mendukung Baek-du.
And at the health center,
Dan di pusat kesehatan,
they give you free medicine if you support Baek-du.
mereka memberi obat gratis jika mendukung Baek-du.
I actually like that.
Aku suka itu.
Still, we can't keep switching sides whenever we visit different stores.
Namun, kita tak bisa berganti pihak tiap mendatangi toko berbeda.
It gives me headaches.
Ini membuatku pusing.
Where are we going, by the way?
Omong-omong, kita mau ke mana?
We're going to match up Jin-su and Baek-du.
Kita akan buat Jin-su dan Baek-du bertanding.
The winner will be the coach.
Pemenangnya akan menjadi pelatih.
That's a great idea.
Itu ide bagus.
Oh, boy. It looks like they've already started a fight.
Astaga. Sepertinya mereka sudah memulai pertengkaran.
You know, about that…
Kau tahu, soal itu…
About the coaching position.
Soal posisi pelatih.
Did Seongwon find a replacement already?
Seongwon sudah mendapatkan pengganti?
-Why do you ask? -Well…
- Kenapa kau bertanya? - Begini…
-Because you-- -You want me to be Seongwon's coach
- Karena kau… - Kau mau aku melatih Seongwon
so you can take this?
agar dapat posisi ini?
Come on, Jin-su. Don't be like that.
Ayolah, Jin-su. Jangan seperti itu.
You see, I'm not interested in the coaching position at all.
Kau tahu, aku sama sekali tak tertarik menjadi pelatih.
I'm really not. But…
Sungguh tidak tertarik. Tapi…
But I have a reason now to…
Tapi kini aku punya alasan untuk…
No.
Tidak.
I'm going to be the coach here, no matter what.
Aku akan menjadi pelatih di sini, apa pun yang terjadi.
Of course. Jin-su, you should do it.
Tentu saja. Jin-su, kau harus melakukannya.
Fine. You have it all then.
Baiklah. Kalau begitu, lakukanlah.
What… Why?
Apa… Kenapa?
-Let's have a match! -A match?
- Mari kita bertanding! - Bertanding?
What?
Apa?
You and I will have a match to decide who should be the coach.
Kita bertanding untuk menentukan siapa yang akan jadi pelatih.
What, aren't you confident you'll win?
Apa? Kau tak percaya diri akan menang?
If you're not,
Jika tidak,
I'll take it as a defeat.
kuanggap kau kalah.
What do you say? Are you up for a match?
Bagaimana menurutmu? Siap bertanding?
-Go for it. -Come on.
- Lakukanlah. - Ayolah.
How can I… Forget it.
Bagaimana bisa aku… Lupakan saja.
Oh, come on.
Ayolah.
What's your answer?
Apa jawabanmu?
I'm not sure.
Aku tidak yakin.
I'm not sure
Aku tak yakin
if you can beat me.
kau bisa mengalahkanku.
-What? -Fine.
- Apa? - Baiklah.
Let's have a match.
Mari bertanding.
We won't know who will win until we wrestle, will we?
Kita tak tahu pemenangnya sampai kita bergulat.
Gosh, I'm excited!
Astaga, aku bersemangat!
It's been ages since we had a match!
Sudah lama sekali kita tidak bertanding!
Am I right? This will be so much fun!
Aku benar, 'kan? Ini akan sangat seru!
All right. We'll have a match!
Baiklah. Kita akan bertanding!
-Are you crazy? -Come on!
- Kau sudah gila? - Ayo!
Settle your tabs, will you?
Bayar tagihan kalian!
It's not even much!
Itu bahkan tidak banyak!
You know what? There's a thin line between bravery and recklessness.
Kau tahu? Berani dan gegabah itu beda tipis.
But in your case, you're so far gone. You're reckless.
Tapi bagimu, kau jauh lebih buruk. Kau gegabah.
Want a bite?
Mau sesuap?
What's wrong with you?
Ada apa denganmu?
Why did you accept it?
Kenapa kau menerimanya?
Do you want to be a coach?
Kau mau menjadi pelatih?
No way.
Tidak.
I've never even dreamed of it.
Bahkan tak pernah kuimpikan.
Then, why? Why did you suddenly decide to do it?
Lantas, kenapa tiba-tiba memutuskan bertanding?
Obviously, I wasn't thinking.
Aku jelas tak berpikir jernih.
I must've been possessed by something.
Pasti aku dirasuki sesuatu.
Possessed by what?
Dirasuki apa?
You don't want to know. It's some evil girl.
Kau tak mau tahu. Semacam gadis jahat.
What are you saying?
Kau ini bicara apa?
You don't have to worry too much, though.
Tapi kau tak perlu begitu khawatir.
I feel bad saying this,
Maaf mengatakan ini,
but not many people actually expect you to win.
tapi tak banyak orang mengharapkanmu menang.
Almost none.
Hampir tak ada.
So don't worry.
Jadi, jangan khawatir.
What about you?
Bagaimana denganmu?
Do you think I'll lose?
Menurutmu aku akan kalah?
And you call yourself a friend?
Kau sebut dirimu temanku?
Darn it.
Sial.
It's impossible to identify that person.
Mustahil mengidentifikasi orang itu.
Should we ask Geosan Precinct for help? They might be able to recognize him.
Mau minta bantuan Polsek Geosan? Mungkin mereka bisa mengenalinya.
Hey, I'm here.
Hei, aku datang.
Come on. Hurry up.
Ayo. Cepatlah.
-Let's go. -Hey.
- Ayo. - Hei.
-Where's Uk? -He left way earlier.
- Di mana Uk? - Dia sudah pergi sejak tadi.
LEFT TO WATCH SSIREUM PAY HONESTLY
PERGI MENONTON SSIREUM BAYAR DENGAN JUJUR
Hey. Come this way.
Hei. Kemarilah.
Hey! I'm here.
Hei! Aku di sini.
-You made it. -Hey.
- Kau datang. - Hei.
Why are you so late?
Kenapa lama sekali?
Where were you?
Dari mana saja kau?
This is amazing. I think we have more of an audience than usual.
Ini hebat. Kurasa penontonnya lebih banyak dari biasanya.
It wasn't like this at my match.
Tak seperti ini di lagaku.
Other people might think there's some great match here.
Orang lain bisa berpikir ada pertandingan besar di sini.
What's the matter?
Ada apa?
Can you believe those guys are sitting there?
Bisa-bisanya mereka duduk di sana.
You're right.
Kau benar.
Do they actually think that Baek-du will win?
Mereka sungguh berpikir Baek-du akan menang?
Well, we all have different opinions, so…
Kita semua punya opini berbeda, jadi…
-He has poor judgment. -He was called a prodigy.
- Penilaiannya buruk. - Dulu dia anak ajaib.
Right.
Benar.
Baek-du sure was born with talent.
Baek-du terlahir dengan bakat.
-Drink some water. -I'm good.
- Minumlah ini. - Tidak perlu.
I have everything here.
Ibu bawa semuanya di sini.
Look at Jin-su's body.
Lihatlah tubuh Jin-su.
He looks so sturdy.
Dia tampak sangat kekar.
The guys in Seongwon told me
Orang-orang di Seongwon memberitahuku
that he's been lifting weights two hours a day since retirement.
dia selama ini angkat beban dua jam sehari sejak pensiun.
-You're kidding. -It's true.
- Kau bercanda. - Itu benar.
No smoking, no alcohol. He's been textbook clean.
Tidak merokok dan minum alkohol. Dia bersih.
He's so fit.
Dia sangat bugar.
Does Baek-du have a chance?
Apa Baek-du punya peluang?
Why not? He's got a great body.
Kenapa tidak? Tubuhnya bagus.
I heard he was born with a body that easily builds muscle.
Kudengar dia terlahir dengan tubuh yang mudah membangun otot.
Right. I also heard from someone
Benar. Aku juga pernah dengar
that Jin-su joined Seongwon in high school because of Baek-du.
Jin-su bergabung di SMA Seongwon karena Baek-du.
Why?
Kenapa?
Because he had never beaten Baek-du until middle school.
Karena dia tak pernah mengalahkan Baek-du sampai SMP.
You got this, Jin-su!
Kau pasti bisa, Jin-su!
You got this!
Kau pasti bisa!
Let's go! My son is the best!
Ayo! Putraku yang terbaik!
GEOSAN-GUN SSIREUM TEAM
TIM SSIREUM GEOSAN-GUN
Hold his satba tight and don't even think of lifting him.
Pegang erat satba-nya dan jangan coba mengangkatnya.
It will be hard because he's heavier.
Akan sulit karena dia lebih berat.
Just let him try Lifting Throw and trip him up so he'll lose balance.
Biarkan dia mencoba Lemparan Banting dan sandung dia agar hilang keseimbangan.
-Okay. -Sounds great.
- Baik. - Ide bagus.
-Are you listening to me? -Yes. Okay.
- Kau mendengarkanku? - Ya. Baiklah.
-Did you really hear what I said? -Yes. Jeez.
- Kau sungguh mendengarkan? - Ya. Astaga.
You look so distracted.
Kau tampak tak fokus.
Listen to your brother.
Dengarkan kakakmu.
Your only problem is that you hold the satba too loosely.
Masalahmu hanyalah kau pegang satba terlalu longgar.
Do you know what a satba is in ssireum? It's the heart of ssireum.
Kau tahu arti satba dalam ssireum? Itu jantungnya ssireum.
Toughen up, okay?
Kuatkan dirimu, ya?
Having a soft heart can be… What's the word?
Jika hatimu terlalu lemah… Apa sebutannya?
Strength. It can be your strength, but this is a match. This world is cruel.
Itu bisa menjadi kekuatanmu, tapi ini pertandingan. Dunia ini kejam.
All right. Baek-du, Jin-su, come on up.
Baiklah. Baek-du, Jin-su, majulah.
Okay? Just keep what I said in mind.
Paham? Ingat saja perkataanku.
-Go, Baek-du! -Go, Jin-su!
- Ayo, Baek-du! - Ayo, Jin-su!
Let's go, Jin-su!
Ayo, Jin-su!
Baek-du, you can do it!
Baek-du, kau pasti bisa!
Geosan's champion, Kwak Jin-su!
Juara Geosan, Kwak Jin-su!
Let's go!
Ayo!
Grab satbas.
Pegang satba-nya.
Jeez. That's a tight grip.
Astaga. Itu cengkeraman yang kuat.
Left knees up.
Angkat lutut kiri.
The grip seems disadvantageous for Baek-du.
Cengkeramannya tampak merugikan Baek-du.
Outer leg! It's an outer leg skill!
Kaki luar! Itu teknik kaki luar!
Baek-du! Jin-su is going to do an outer leg skill!
Baek-du! Jin-su akan melakukan teknik kaki luar!
He'll go for his outer leg.
Dia mengincar kaki luarnya.
Jin-su!
Jin-su!
-Hey. -Look at that.
- Hei. - Lihat itu.
-Oh, come on! -Jin-su's leg gave out.
- Ayolah! - Kaki Jin-su melemah.
Just throw that little brat!
Banting saja berandal itu!
-Go, Jin-su!
- Ayo, Jin-su!
Please…
Kumohon…
-What? -Nothing.
- Apa? - Bukan apa-apa.
He's falling a bit short.
Dia sedikit tertinggal.
Nice!
Bagus!
That's my son! You rock!
Itu baru putraku! Kau hebat!
That's my boy!
Itu putraku!
What was that just now?
Apa itu tadi?
Jin-su must be quite surprised.
Jin-su pasti cukup terkejut.
Kwak Jin-su for the win!
Kwak Jin-su menang!
Oh, no. Baek-du.
Astaga. Baek-du.
Good job, Baek-du.
Usaha yang bagus, Baek-du.
-Was that a good job? -Of course it was.
- Itu usaha yang bagus? - Tentu.
Given their weight difference, he did an incredible job.
Melihat perbedaan bobot mereka, dia bermain dengan baik.
You would've won if you'd grabbed the satba more tightly, you fool.
Kau menang jika pegang satba-nya lebih erat lagi, Bodoh.
Kim Baek-du has delivered a performance far beyond our expectations.
Kim Baek-du memberikan performa di luar ekspektasi kita.
I was going to turn off the camera, but I'll keep it on for now.
Aku tadinya mau mematikan kamera, tapi kunyalakan saja dulu.
Relax and focus. Okay?
Tenang dan fokuslah. Mengerti?
Now, come on up, boys.
Silakan maju.
Listen to Geum-gang. Get the head start.
Dengarkan Geum-gang. Curi start.
Keep it smooth.
Bergerak yang mulus.
Grab the satba tight.
Pegang erat satba-nya.
Go, Baek-du!
Ayo, Baek-du!
You got this!
Kau pasti bisa!
-Let's go! -Let's turn this around!
- Ayo! - Mari balikkan keadaan!
Let's go!
Ayo!
Baek-du!
Baek-du!
Let's win this and go eat at my restaurant.
Mari menangkan ini dan makan di restoranku.
Grab the leg satbas.
Pegang satba kakinya.
Baek-du, satba!
Baek-du, satba!
Baek-du, pull your shoulders in.
Baek-du, tarik masuk bahumu.
-Shoulders. -Grab the waist satbas.
- Bahu. - Pegang satba pinggang.
-Nice. -Jin-su!
- Bagus. - Jin-su!
Nice satba grip.
Cengkeraman bagus.
-Left knees up! -Nice shoulders.
- Angkat lutut kiri! - Bagus.
Stand up.
Berdiri.
Let's go.
Ayo.
Hold out with your core! Nice!
Tahan dengan otot inti! Bagus!
That was amazing.
Itu bagus sekali.
Why are you showing your skills at an unofficial match after retirement?
Kenapa pamerkan keahlianmu di laga tak resmi setelah pensiun?
Right, Father? Father, are you crying?
Bukan begitu, Ayah? Ayah menangis?
-Honey. -Yes?
- Sayang. - Ya?
Who do you think will win?
Siapa yang akan menang?
I'm not sure. They seem evenly matched.
Entahlah. Mereka tampak seimbang.
Do you need water?
Kau butuh air?
Jeez, what's gotten into Baek-du?
Astaga, apa yang merasuki Baek-du?
Tell me about it.
Benar sekali.
Jin-su seems to be in pretty good shape.
Jin-su tampak cukup bugar.
-See? You can do it. -What's going on?
- Lihat? Kau bisa. - Apa yang terjadi?
Grab the satba properly. Okay?
Pegang satba-nya dengan benar. Paham?
Yu-gyeong, who do you think will win?
Yu-gyeong, menurutmu siapa yang akan menang?
I'm not sure.
Entahlah.
Come on. Then, who do you wish would win?
Ayolah. Lantas, kau berharap siapa yang menang?
-Keep it in. -Very good.
- Terus tahan. - Bagus.
Stay strong, okay?
Tetaplah kuat, ya?
It's called Outer Leg Back Satba Snatching.
Itu Tarikan Satba Punggung Kaki Luar.
It's a hard combination skill.
Itu kombinasi teknik sulit.
-I can't believe you used that. -Now, it's the last round.
- Sulit kupercaya kau memakai itu. - Ini ronde terakhir.
-Getting the hang of it? -Come on up now.
- Kini kau menguasainya? - Majulah.
-All right. -Keep the momentum.
- Baiklah. - Jaga momentumnya.
Let's go for it once again!
Mari lakukan sekali lagi!
Let's go!
Ayo!
You can do it.
Kau pasti bisa.
Go, Jin-su! You got this, my boy!
Ayo, Jin-su! Kau pasti bisa, Putraku!
Make some noise!
Bersoraklah!
My gosh, I think my heart is going to explode.
Astaga, kurasa jantungku hampir meledak.
I told him not to skip breakfast.
Sudah kubilang jangan lupa sarapan.
-Left knees up. -Now he's getting tired.
- Angkat lutut. - Kini dia lelah.
You got this!
Kau pasti bisa!
Do it properly. Let's start over.
Lakukan dengan benar. Mari ulangi.
Good luck!
Semoga berhasil!
Mr. Kim Baek-du!
Pak Kim Baek-du!
What?
Apa?
What's happening?
Apa yang terjadi?
Yes?
Ya?
Could we talk for a moment?
Bisa kita bicara sebentar?
Come over here.
Kemarilah.
-They're in the middle of a match. -Here.
- Mereka sedang bertanding. - Ini.
Oh, you're a police officer.
Kalian polisi.
Yes. Please come this way.
Ya. Silakan kemari.
What are the cops doing here?
Kenapa polisi datang ke sini?
We need to check a few things with you
Kami mau memeriksa beberapa hal
regarding the fatal accident that happened here recently.
terkait kecelakaan yang terjadi baru-baru ini.
Please follow us to the police station.
Silakan ikut kami ke kantor polisi.
-The fatal accident? -Yes.
- Kecelakaan fatal? - Ya.
What are they doing here?
Kenapa mereka ada di sini?
What are you going to do?
Kau mau apa?
Just stay here.
Tetaplah di sini.
Why would you take my boy?
Kenapa kalian membawa putraku?
-Explain what this is about. -Come on, don't be like this.
- Jelaskan soal apa ini. - Ayolah, jangan seperti ini.
If you keep doing this, we'll have to arrest you
Jika tidak, kami harus menahan kalian
for obstruction of justice.
karena halangi penyelidikan.
So please step aside for now.
Jadi, menyingkirlah untuk saat ini.
Did you bring a warrant?
Kalian bawa surat perintah?
This is ridiculous.
Ini tak masuk akal.
It's not what you think it is.
Ini tak seperti dugaan kalian.
It won't take long.
Ini tak akan lama.
We just need to check a few things.
Kami hanya perlu periksa beberapa hal.
-This isn't obstruction. -Let's go.
- Ini bukan menghalangi. - Ayo.
-No. -Please come here.
- Tidak. - Silakan kemari.
-Hey. -No, wait.
- Hei. - Tidak, tunggu.
Wait. Do I…
Tunggu. Apakah aku…
Do I go like this?
Aku harus pergi seperti ini?
What on earth did Baek-du do wrong?
Apa sebenarnya kesalahan Baek-du?
They said it isn't because he did something wrong.
Mereka bilang bukan karena dia berbuat kesalahan.
They just wanted to check something.
Mereka hanya ingin periksa sesuatu.
Then they would've checked it there,
Mereka bisa saja periksa di sana,
instead of taking him to the police station.
alih-alih membawanya ke kantor polisi.
It's not a big deal.
Itu bukan masalah besar.
You know there was an accident here recently, right?
Kalian tahu ada kecelakaan di sini belum lama ini, 'kan?
Apparently, the dead guy and Baek-du ran into each other,
Tampaknya, pria yang tewas itu dan Baek-du sempat bertemu
and it was captured on the CCTV by the coast.
dan itu terekam di CCTV di tepi pantai.
-By the coast? -Yes.
- Di tepi pantai? - Ya.
See, Sarge? I told you there must be--
Dengar itu, Sersan? Sudah kubilang…
They're just asking him
Mereka hanya bertanya
a few questions about that, so don't worry about it.
beberapa hal soal itu, jadi, jangan khawatir.
They say it's not a big deal.
Mereka bilang itu bukan hal besar.
Man.
Astaga.
Maybe we should get him a lawyer.
Mungkin kita harus carikan dia pengacara.
Do any of you know a lawyer?
Kalian punya kenalan pengacara?
Come on. The only people anyone here knows are ssireum wrestlers.
Ayolah. Orang yang dikenal semua warga di sini hanyalah pegulat ssireum.
To us, lawyers are like
Bagi kami, pengacara itu bagaikan
-unicorns in fairy tales… -Right.
- unikorn di kisah peri… - Benar.
Wait. That reminds me.
Tunggu. Aku baru ingat.
My cousin's sister-in-law.
Kakak ipar sepupuku
-She's a lawyer. -Wait!
- pengacara. - Tunggu!
About that day, he won't be of any help.
Soal hari itu, dia tak akan membantu.
What are you saying?
Apa maksudmu?
Why? What is it?
Kenapa? Ada apa?
What's wrong with him?
Ada apa dengannya?
That day, Baek-du was drunk.
Hari itu, Baek-du mabuk.
Mr. Kim Baek-du.
Pak Kim Baek-du.
You know
Kau tahu
that someone died recently
belum lama ini seseorang tewas
in your neighborhood, right?
di lingkunganmu, 'kan?
Yes, I heard about it.
Ya, aku mendengarnya.
And according to our investigation,
Dan menurut penyelidikan kami,
you were the last person to see Choi Chil-seong on that day.
kaulah orang terakhir yang melihat Choi Chil-seong hari itu.
That's why you're here.
Itu alasanmu ada di sini.
I was?
Aku?
Yes.
Ya.
Around 10:00 p.m. that night, you walked along Geosan Coastal Road, right?
Sekitar pukul 22.00, kau menyusuri Jalan Pantai Geosan, 'kan?
We verified that from the CCTV footage.
Kami memverifikasinya dari rekaman CCTV.
Mr. Kim.
Pak Kim.
Depending on what you say now,
Tergantung dari perkataanmu sekarang,
you can be in serious trouble.
kau bisa terlibat masalah besar.
So,
Jadi,
please tell me everything you remember about what happened that day.
tolong sebutkan semua yang kau ingat soal kejadian hari itu.
I don't remember.
Aku tak ingat.
What?
Apa?
But it happened only recently.
Tapi itu terjadi belum lama ini.
No, Detective.
Tidak, Detektif.
That day, I drank so much and…
Hari itu, aku mabuk berat dan…
How much did you drink?
Seberapa banyak kau minum alkohol?
This much soju in a beer glass.
Soju sebanyak ini dalam gelas bir.
Come on.
Ayolah.
That's not enough to have a blackout.
Itu tak cukup untuk pingsan.
To me, that's a fatal dose.
Bagiku, itu dosis yang fatal.
Then, do you have any foggy memories that you recall?
Kalau begitu, ada ingatan samar yang bisa kau ingat?
Gosh, I really don't remember anything.
Astaga, aku sungguh tak ingat apa pun.
Give me a minute.
Beri aku waktu.
That day,
Hari itu,
I drank alcohol,
aku minum alkohol
and my friends yelled at me.
dan teman-temanku meneriakiku.
When I woke up, I was startled by my mom's face.
Saat terbangun, aku terkejut melihat wajah ibuku.
Then, the bruise on my waist.
Lalu ada lebam di pinggangku.
-And… -A bruise?
- Dan… - Lebam?
Yes. I don't know how I got it,
Ya. Entah dari mana kudapatkan itu,
but I had a small injury here. Let me just…
tapi ada cedera kecil di sini. Biar aku…
Could you have had a fight?
Mungkinkah kau terlibat perkelahian?
A fight?
Perkelahian?
Actually, we went over the CCTV footage thoroughly
Sebenarnya, kami mengulas rekaman CCTV-nya dengan teliti,
and saw that you and Choi Chil-seong
kemudian melihatmu dan Choi Chil-seong
had a scuffle on the road that night.
berkelahi di jalanan malam itu.
Why did you fight him?
Kenapa berkelahi dengannya?
I guess not yet.
Kurasa belum selesai.
What's taking so long?
Kenapa lama sekali?
Stop shaking your leg.
Berhenti menggoyangkan kaki.
Captain Chu said she'd take care of it.
Kapten Chu bilang dia akan mengurusnya.
They'll come out once they're done.
Mereka akan keluar begitu selesai.
What if he gets scared and says something stupid?
Bagaimana jika dia ketakutan dan mengatakan hal bodoh?
Yu-gyeong.
Yu-gyeong.
I've been wondering this for a while.
Aku sudah lama memikirkan ini.
Do you--
Apa kau…
That's…
Itu…
What's she doing here?
Apa yang dia lakukan di sini?
It looks like
Sepertinya
Kim Baek-du really doesn't remember anything.
Kim Baek-du sungguh tak ingat apa pun.
What do we do?
Bagaimana ini?
Hey, Chu Mi-suk.
Hei, Chu Mi-suk.
You must have a lot of free time.
Waktu luangmu pasti banyak.
Is there nothing to do in Seoul?
Tak ada pekerjaan di Seoul?
Why did you all have to come down here at the same time?
Kenapa kalian semua harus kemari pada saat bersamaan?
So tell me. Who is he?
Katakanlah. Siapa dia?
We identified that man for you,
Kami mengidentifikasi pria itu untukmu,
so shouldn't you at least tell us what's going on?
bukankah seharusnya kau beri tahu kami ada apa?
He's a suspect in the murder of Choi Chil-seong,
Dia tersangka pembunuhan Choi Chil-seong
whom we've chased for years.
yang bertahun-tahun kami incar.
Choi Chil-seong?
Choi Chil-seong?
Choi Chil-seong…
Choi Chil-seong…
The name sounds familiar.
Nama itu tak asing.
He's a match-fixer who set up
Dia pelaku pengaturan laga
a gambling scheme worth billions of won, involving politicians.
skema perjudian miliaran won dan melibatkan politikus.
What?
Apa?
It's a confidential investigation,
Ini penyelidikan rahasia,
so I couldn't give you a heads-up. I apologize.
jadi, aku tak bisa berikan penjelasan. Maaf.
And that man is the suspect?
Dan pria itu tersangkanya?
Salute.
Hormat.
What the…
Apa-apaan…
We're in the middle of an interrogation.
Kami sedang menginterogasi.
Well, it's just that…
Maaf, begini…
There's someone insisting she has something to say.
Ada orang yang berkeras ingin katakan sesuatu.
-Say what? -Well…
- Mengatakan apa? - Itu…
She wants to say something about this case.
Dia ingin mengatakan sesuatu soal kasus ini.
She says she thinks she saw that man on the day of the incident.
Dia pikir dia melihat pria itu pada hari kecelakaan.
This won't do. Hey, Uk.
Tidak bisa begini. Hei, Uk.
Can you try reaching out to that distant relative of your cousin
Bisa kau coba hubungi kerabat jauh sepupumu
that you talked about?
yang kau bilang tadi?
-Right. -Okay.
- Benar. - Baiklah.
Well, I guess
Kurasa
-it's finally my turn to step up. -Where is she?
- ini giliranku membantu. - Di mana dia?
She was sitting here earlier.
Dia duduk di sini tadi.
Right. Where did she go?
Benar. Ke mana perginya dia?
The restroom, maybe?
Mungkin ke toilet?
Are you asking me?
Kau bertanya kepadaku?
So why are you here again?
Jadi, kenapa kau kemari?
I saw Baek-du with the dead man that day.
Aku melihat Baek-du dengan pria yang tewas itu hari itu.
On the coastal road.
Di jalan tepi pantai.
Are you sure you saw them?
Kau yakin melihat mereka?
Why else would I come all the way here at this hour?
Untuk apa lagi aku datang jauh-jauh kemari selarut ini?
Then, why didn't you say anything until now?
Lantas, kenapa kau baru bicara sekarang?
You never said you saw the two of them together that day.
Kau tak pernah bilang melihat keduanya bersama hari itu.
I didn't know it was that man
Aku tak tahu pria itulah
who was with Baek-du that night.
yang bersama Baek-du malam itu.
But after hearing what people were saying,
Tapi setelah mendengar perkataan orang-orang,
I came to realize that what I saw that night
aku menyadari yang kulihat malam itu
may have something to do with why Baek-du was brought here.
mungkin ada kaitannya dengan alasan Baek-du dibawa kemari.
So what is it that you saw?
Jadi, apa yang kau lihat?
That night, I was doing yoga on the rooftop of the building.
Malam itu, aku sedang melakukan yoga di atap gedung.
Now, count to ten.
Sekarang, hitung sampai sepuluh.
Take a deep breath in.
Tarik napas dalam.
One.
Satu.
Now, exhale. Two.
Sekarang, buang napas. Dua.
Du-sik!
Du-sik!
-Three. -Oh Du-sik!
- Tiga. - Oh Du-sik!
-Four. -Du-sik!
- Empat. - Du-sik!
And I heard some crazy man shouting so late at night.
Dan aku mendengar pria gila berteriak pada larut malam.
Du-sik!
Du-sik!
Oh Du-sik!
Oh Du-sik!
-It was Baek-du. -Oh Du-sik!
- Pria itu Baek-du. - Oh Du-sik!
He was obviously wasted.
Dia jelas mabuk berat.
Oh Du-sik!
Oh Du-sik!
He was staggering onto the road, unaware of a car approaching.
Dia terhuyung di jalan itu, tak tahu ada mobil mendekat.
-He could've been hit at any time. -Car…
- Dia bisa saja tertabrak. - Mobil…
But he got lucky. He didn't die.
Tapi dia beruntung. Dia tak mati.
It seemed they had a bit of a scuffle, though.
Tapi sepertinya mereka sempat berkelahi.
Mr. Kim.
Pak Kim.
We even have a witness in our police station right now.
Kami bahkan punya saksi di kantor polisi saat ini.
-A witness? -Yes.
- Saksi? - Ya.
According to the witness,
Menurut saksi itu,
the two of you had a scuffle on the coastal road.
kalian sempat berkelahi di jalan tepi pantai.
-But… -So I asked the witness,
- Tapi… - Jadi, kutanya saksinya,
"Why were they fighting?"
"Kenapa mereka bertengkar?"
Then, the witness said you were trying
Lantas, saksinya bilang kau berusaha
to give something to Choi Chil-seong.
memberi sesuatu kepada Choi Chil-seong.
I was?
Benarkah?
-Give him what? -Money.
- Memberinya apa? - Uang.
It was money.
Uang.
Money?
Uang?
Why would he try to give him money?
Kenapa dia ingin memberinya uang?
I don't know.
Entahlah.
I just thought he was doing that because he was drunk.
Aku hanya berpikir dia melakukan itu karena mabuk.
By the way, you must have really good eyesight.
Omong-omong, penglihatanmu pasti bagus sekali.
What?
Apa?
You could see that it was money from the rooftop?
Kau bisa melihat itu uang dari atap?
Of course I couldn't.
Tentu saja tidak.
Then, how did you know it was money?
Lantas, bagaimana kau tahu itu uang?
How could I not
Bagaimana bisa aku tak tahu
when he was shouting out so loud about it?
jika dia berteriak kencang soal itu?
Take it! You should take it!
Ambillah! Kau harus menerimanya!
What's going on?
Apa yang terjadi?
-At the restaurant… -What is he trying to give him?
- Di restoran… - Dia ingin memberinya apa?
Here! 40,000 won!
Ini! 40.000 won!
Take it.
Terimalah!
Aren't you going to take the 40,000 won?
Kau tak mau menerima 40.000 won ini?
Did he say "40,000 won"?
Dia bilang "40.000 won"?
Mr. Kim.
Pak Kim.
What was that 40,000 won about?
Ada apa dengan 40.000 won itu?
What was it about that money
Ada apa dengan uang itu
that you had to try so hard to give to him?
hingga kau berusaha begitu keras memberikannya kepadanya?
This is so frustrating.
Ini sangat memusingkan.
Mr. Kim.
Pak Kim.
Could you please speak honestly now?
Bisa kau bicara jujur sekarang?
We even have a witness now, so it'll only make things worse if you don't tell us.
Kami bahkan punya saksi sekarang, jadi, ini akan memburuk jika kau diam.
Also, I need to know the truth
Aku juga harus tahu kebenarannya
to be able to help you. You know what I mean?
agar bisa membantumu. Kau paham maksudku?
Yes. You're right.
Ya. Kau benar.
Actually, I…
Sebenarnya, aku…
I did something.
melakukan sesuatu.
Did what? Did you hit Choi?
Melakukan apa? Kau memukul Choi?
No, I didn't hit him.
Tidak, aku tak memukulnya.
I did…
Aku…
-I did something bad. -Come on.
- Aku melakukan hal buruk. - Ayolah.
What do you mean?
Apa maksudmu?
Could you speak loudly and clearly?
Bisa bicara lebih keras dan jelas?
I stole the money!
Aku mencuri uang itu!
I kept the change!
Aku menyimpan kembaliannya!
Here's your change, 40,000--
Ini kembalianmu, 40.000…
What? Where did he go?
Apa? Ke mana perginya dia?
Give me the plates. How many chopsticks?
Kemarikan piringnya. Berapa sumpit?
What's wrong with him?
Ada apa dengannya?
What am I supposed to do with this change?
Aku harus bagaimana dengan kembalian ini?
I can't… He was supposed to take it.
Aku tak bisa… Dia seharusnya menerimanya.
It's actually been weighing on me.
Itu sebenarnya membebaniku.
Then, after a few days,
Lalu setelah beberapa hari,
I heard in the neighborhood meeting that the man died.
kudengar di pertemuan warga pria itu tewas.
On the day after the reunion at that.
Terlebih pada hari setelah reuni.
He threw himself into the reservoir.
Dia melompat ke waduk itu.
Hearing that story
Mendengar kisah itu
made me feel so uncomfortable.
membuatku merasa sangat tidak nyaman.
So I tried to give the money back many times.
Jadi, aku berulang kali berusaha mengembalikan uangnya.
But…
Tapi…
Ms. Lim isn't usually around the restaurant.
Bu Lim biasanya tak ada di restoran.
But since then, she's always been hanging out in the restaurant.
Tapi sejak saat itu, dia selalu berada di restoran.
Believe me.
Percayalah padaku.
It was driving me crazy too.
Itu juga membuatku gila.
Detective, I haven't spent that money yet.
Detektif, aku belum menggunakan uang itu.
Could you please let it slide?
Bisa kau maafkan itu?
Billions of won? Murder suspect?
Miliaran won? Tersangka pembunuhan?
Chu, we need to talk.
Chu, kita harus bicara.
Baek-du's been released!
Baek-du dibebaskan!
He's clear of all suspicions.
Dia aman dari semua kecurigaan.
See? I knew he'd be freed.
Lihat? Aku tahu dia akan dibebaskan.
We didn't have to stay here until so late.
Kita tak perlu ada di sini sampai larut.
We were all worried for nothing, after all.
Sia-sia saja kita khawatir.
-I know, right? -Well, I'm just glad nothing happened.
- Benar. - Aku lega tak terjadi apa pun.
By the way, Baek-du sure is unlucky when it comes to ssireum.
Omong-omong, Baek-du memang tak beruntung jika menyangkut ssireum.
He was on a roll for once, and look what happened. The cops suddenly took him.
Dia akhirnya hebat dan lihat yang terjadi. Polisi tiba-tiba membawanya.
So who's going to be the coach now?
Jadi, sekarang siapa pelatihnya?
Well…
Soal itu…
What's there to think about?
Apa yang harus dipikirkan?
Strictly speaking, Baek-du threw in the towel.
Sudah jelas, Baek-du mengakui kekalahan.
-Right. -But it's such a shame.
- Benar. - Tapi sayang sekali.
Baek-du actually seemed to be better than Jin-su earlier.
Baek-du tampaknya lebih baik dari Jin-su tadi.
She's right. Baek-du almost beat Jin-su.
Dia benar. Baek-du hampir mengalahkan Jin-su.
Whatever.
Terserahlah.
I don't know.
Aku tak tahu lagi.
-Good night. -Bye.
- Selamat malam. - Sampai nanti.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Let's go home.
Mari pulang.
Gosh, what a day.
Astaga, hari yang melelahkan.
-Thank you. -Good night.
- Terima kasih. - Selamat malam.
-All right. -Bye.
- Baiklah. - Dah.
-Come on. Let's go. -What?
- Ayo. Mari pergi. - Apa?
-Do you not hear me? -I do.
- Kau tak dengar? - Dengar.
-Let's go! -Okay.
- Ayo! - Baiklah.
Hey.
Hei.
Yes?
Ya?
I'll bring the 40,000 won back tomorrow.
Akan kukembalikan 40.000 won itu besok.
Come on. Don't be ridiculous.
Ayolah. Jangan konyol.
If that's what you think,
Jika itu yang kau pikirkan,
I should also pay you for all the herbal tea I had at your place.
aku juga harus bayar semua teh herbal yang kuminum di rumahmu.
This is not the same as that.
Itu tidak sama.
Seriously.
Astaga.
Baek-du is just hilarious.
Baek-du lucu sekali.
If he was going to steal some cash, he should've stolen big.
Jika dia mau mencuri uang, seharusnya ambil yang banyak.
Why only 40,000 won?
Kenapa hanya 40.000 won?
My goodness. It's just so embarrassing.
Astaga. Itu memalukan.
I'm mortified to death. You know?
Aku sangat malu. Kau tahu?
Come on. He's cute.
Ayolah. Dia manis.
What are you saying?
Apa maksudmu?
This must be why everyone likes Baek-du.
Ini pasti alasan semua orang menyukai Baek-du.
That boy is just adorable.
Anak itu sangat manis.
I'm sure you don't know
Aku yakin kau tak tahu
that Jin-su was always outplayed by Baek-du growing up.
Jin-su selalu dikalahkan Baek-du saat kecil.
No way. If anyone, it would've been Baek-du.
Tidak mungkin. Jika benar, pasti Baek-du yang kalah.
Jin-su has always been good.
Jin-su selalu hebat.
Oh, I don't know.
Entahlah.
I could just see that.
Aku bisa melihatnya.
So this time,
Jadi, kali ini,
I almost hated Baek-du.
aku hampir membenci Baek-du.
But he wouldn't let me. Baek-du is just too cute.
Tapi dia tak membiarkanku. Baek-du terlalu manis.
Why don't you be his mom then?
Lantas kenapa kau tak menjadi ibunya saja?
I'll pay you for it.
Akan kubayar kau untuk itu.
Jin-suk.
Jin-suk.
There's a poem that goes,
Ada puisi yang berbunyi,
"Beautiful when looked at from afar. Beautiful when looked at briefly."
"Indah jika dilihat dari jauh. Indah jika dilihat sesaat."
That's what Baek-du is like.
Seperti itulah Baek-du.
What the hell are you talking about?
Kau ini bicara apa?
Come on. I used to love literature.
Ayolah. Dahulu aku suka sastra.
Oh, whatever.
Terserahlah.
Ask me why I live…
Tanya kenapa aku hidup…
There you go.
Kau mulai lagi.
I will dance tonight
Aku akan menari malam ini
I will steal and steal big
Aku akan mencuri banyak sekali
He is coming
Dia datang
Mr. Kim Baek-du is walking out now.
Pak Kim Baek-du keluar sekarang.
Stop that.
Hentikan.
-Congratulations on your release. -Stop.
- Selamat sudah bebas. - Hentikan.
You did a great job.
Kau sudah berusaha keras.
-Dad. -Hey.
- Ayah. - Hei.
Eat this.
Makanlah ini.
-What's that? -Tofu.
- Apa itu? - Tahu.
-Put that away. -Hey.
- Singkirkan itu. - Hei.
And you. What are you filming this time?
Kau juga. Kau merekam apa kali ini?
"The moment Kim Baek-du got released."
"Momen saat Kim Baek-du dibebaskan."
When I start losing subscribers, I'll post this video with this clickbait title.
Jika pelangganku berkurang, akan kuunggah ini dengan judul umpan klik.
It'll be effective.
Itu pasti ampuh.
-What are you saying? -Don't touch the camera.
- Apa maksudmu? - Jangan sentuh kameranya.
Wait. I think I got a nervous stomach.
Tunggu. Kurasa perutku mulas.
I need to use the restroom.
Aku harus ke toilet.
Just poop at home.
Buang air besar saja di rumah.
No, I can't hold it for that long. I'll be quick.
Tidak bisa kutahan lama. Sebentar saja.
-Hey, come on! -Mr. Kim Baek-du.
- Hei, ayolah! - Pak Kim Baek-du!
He can explode at any time now.
Dia bisa buang air kapan saja.
-Will you please stop? -Don't touch my camera.
- Bisa hentikan? - Jangan sentuh kameraku.
Now, Kim Baek-du is walking into the police station of his own will.
Sekarang, Kim Baek-du memasuki kantor polisi dengan sukarela.
Darn it.
Sial.
Where is it?
Di mana toiletnya?
Baek-du.
Baek-du.
What?
Apa?
Hey.
Hei.
What are you doing here?
Kenapa kau ada di sini?
Wait. Are you the witness?
Tunggu. Kau saksinya?
You owe me one.
Kau berutang budi kepadaku.
You better pay me back later.
Sebaiknya balas aku nanti.
What…
Apa…
Darn it.
Sial.
MEN'S RESTROOM
TOILET PRIA
Come on.
Ayolah.
It's been so long.
Sudah lama kita tak berjumpa.
Let's go grab some food together.
Mari makan bersama.
Maybe next time.
Mungkin lain kali.
I need to head back now.
Aku harus kembali sekarang.
Man.
Astaga.
Mi-suk, you haven't changed. You're still so cold.
Mi-suk, kau belum berubah. Kau masih begitu dingin.
Mi-suk?
Mi-suk?
Chu Mi-suk…
Chu Mi-suk…
That Mi-suk?
Mi-suk yang itu?
About what I said earlier,
Soal perkataanku tadi,
please make sure to keep it secret.
pastikanlah untuk merahasiakannya.
She's Du-sik's mother-in-law.
Dia ibu mertua Du-sik.
Hey, did you eat the tofu?
Hei, kau sudah makan tahunya?
KIM GEUM-GANG FIRST GEUMGANG-CLASS CHAMPIONSHIP
KIM GEUM-GANG KEJUARAAN KELAS GEUMGANG PERTAMA
24-HOUR SCENE
TKP 24 JAM
EPISODE 157 THE PICKPOCKET'S TRUTH
EPISODE 157 KEBENARAN PENCOPET
We received reports
Kami menerima laporan
of rampant pickpocketing around the subway station
soal maraknya pencopetan di stasiun kereta bawah tanah
and went to investigate in hopes of gathering information.
dan pergi menyelidikinya dengan harapan mendapatkan informasi.
Most pickpockets' eyes
Kebanyakan mata pencopet
are fixed on people's belongings
terfokus pada barang-barang
such as handbags, rather than people.
seperti tas, alih-alih orang.
And they are often looking around.
Dan mereka sering melihat sekeliling.
They sometimes skip trains,
Mereka melewatkan kereta
and only move when it's crowded.
dan baru bergerak saat ramai.
That loser calls me by my name so rudely. Damn it.
Pecundang itu begitu tak sopan memanggil namaku. Sial.
That's not how you treat someone who saved you from getting stabbed.
Bukan begitu cara perlakukan orang yang mencegahmu ditikam.
We don't have much time. They won't be keeping this secret for long.
Waktu kita sedikit. Mereka tak akan lama menyimpan rahasia ini.
We've got to move fast.
Kita harus bertindak cepat.
Words can easily spread.
Kabar bisa cepat tersebar.
You can go now. I'll have a smoke before I go.
Kalian pergilah. Aku akan merokok sebelum pergi.
-Yes, Captain.
- Baik, Kapten.
You can go too.
Kalian juga boleh pergi.
-Wait, Captain. -Yes.
- Tunggu, Kapten. - Ya.
I have something to tell you.
Ada yang harus kukatakan.
You can go first.
Pergilah dahulu.
When only one person leaves a group,
Saat hanya satu orang meninggalkan kelompok,
usually, the rest talk behind that person's back.
biasanya, yang lain membicarakan hal buruk orang itu.
He must've told me to go so he could bad-mouth me.
Itu pasti agar dia bisa menjelekkanku.
How petty he is. He's just…
Dia licik sekali. Dia…
What's this now?
Apa lagi sekarang?
What's he doing there? He should be eating some tofu at home.
Kenapa dia di sana? Seharusnya dia makan tahu di rumah.
Hey!
Hei!
Why are you so late? I've been waiting for you for a while.
Kenapa kau lama sekali? Aku sudah lama menunggumu.
Why? Do you have something to say to me?
Kenapa? Ada yang ingin kau katakan?
Do you, by any chance…
Apakah kau…
No.
Tidak.
We need to talk.
Kita harus bicara.
So what is it?
Jadi, ada apa?
Well…
Begini…
It's about Yu-gyeong.
Ini soal Yu-gyeong.
Oh Yu-gyeong? What about her?
Oh Yu-gyeong? Ada apa dengannya?
You know something, don't you?
Kau tahu sesuatu, Bu?
Me? What do I know?
Aku? Apa yang kutahu?
The reason why Yu-gyeong came here.
Alasan Yu-gyeong datang kemari.
Isn't that why you approved this investigation?
Itu alasanmu menerima penyelidikan ini, 'kan?
You know that this is a pretty reckless plan.
Kau tahu ini rencana yang gegabah.
What are you talking about?
Apa maksudmu?
Anyway, what made you think so?
Apa yang membuatmu berpikir begitu?
Did something happen?
Sesuatu terjadi?
No, nothing special. It's just that…
Tidak ada yang istimewa, hanya saja…
Things just looked a bit…
Semuanya agak…
About Kim Baek-du, the guy who was here for the interview.
Soal Kim Baek-du, pria yang diwawancarai di sini.
Yes. What about him?
Ya. Ada apa dengannya?
I think there's something going on
Kurasa terjadi sesuatu
between him and Yu-gyeong.
antara dia dan Yu-gyeong.
Gosh, why…
Astaga, kenapa…
-Were you always this strong? -Come on.
- Kau memang sekuat ini? - Ayolah.
-Let me… -Just come here.
- Lepaskan… - Kemarilah.
Let go of me!
Lepaskan aku!
Jeez, you're really strong.
Astaga, kau sangat kuat.
What is it?
Ada apa?
Just tell me already.
Katakan saja sekarang.
I know this can be
Aku tahu ini mungkin
all sudden and unexpected, but…
sangat tiba-tiba dan tak terduga, tapi…
But what?
Tapi apa?
You know
Kau tahu
we grew up together.
kita tumbuh bersama.
And we share a lot of memories. Right?
Dan kita berbagi banyak kenangan, 'kan?
What are you trying to say?
Apa sebenarnya maksudmu?
Du-sik.
Du-sik.
Are you…
Apakah kau…
You mean there's something romantic going on between them?
Maksudmu, ada hal romantis di antara mereka?
Seriously, she's dating a guy in this situation?
Dia mengencani pria dalam situasi ini?
No, that's not it.
Bukan begitu.
Jeez, you and Yu-gyeong are so similar.
Astaga, kau dan Yu-gyeong sangat mirip.
What is it then?
Lantas, apa?
I just feel like
Aku hanya merasa
they already knew each other.
mereka sudah lama saling kenal.
They already knew each other?
Mereka sudah saling kenal?
Yes. So I'm just worried
Ya. Jadi, aku khawatir
that Kim Baek-du might find out what we're doing here.
Kim Baek-du mungkin tahu yang kita lakukan di sini.
No way.
Tak mungkin.
From what I saw earlier, he seemed somewhat innocent.
Dari yang kulihat tadi, dia terlihat cukup polos.
True, but…
Memang benar, tapi…
People like him can be pretty sharp.
Orang seperti dia bisa sangat jeli.
They look slow on the outside,
Mereka tampak lamban dari luar,
but are actually deeply intuitive.
tapi sebenarnya sangat intuitif.
Are you…
Apakah kau…
a cop?
seorang polisi?
-You are, right? -What?
- Benar, 'kan? - Apa?
That face means you are.
Ekspresimu itu artinya benar.
You are a cop.
Kau polisi.
Wait, how did you…
Tunggu, bagaimana kau…
How did you know?
Bagaimana kau bisa tahu?
Does it matter?
Apa itu penting?
It does.
Itu penting.
So, tell me. How did you find out?
Katakanlah. Bagaimana kau tahu?
Your mother-in-law.
Ibu mertuamu.
She's that woman.
Dia wanita itu.
Mi-suk.
Mi-suk.
Your role model.
Panutanmu.
What? You're surprised?
Apa? Kau terkejut?
I still have one more question to ask you.
Masih ada satu hal yang mau kutanya.
Du-sik.
Du-sik.
You…
Kau…
You're not married, right?
Kau belum menikah, 'kan?
What?
Apa?
And when they're being intuitive,
Dan saat mereka sangat intuitif,
it's impossible to fool them.
mustahil membodohi mereka.
LIKE FLOWERS IN SAND
LIKE FLOWERS IN SAND
I, Kim Baek-du,
Aku, Kim Baek-du,
announce that I'm back on the Geosan-gun Ssireum Team
mengumumkan aku kembali ke Tim Ssireum Geosan-gun
as of today!
per hari ini!
Let's go!
Semangat!
Kim Baek-du!
Kim Baek-du!
Why did you come back if you don't even know the basics?
Kenapa kau kembali jika bahkan tak tahu dasarnya?
It hasn't even been that long since the reservoir incident.
Insiden waduk itu belum begitu lama terjadi.
I'm hearing weird rumors.
Aku mendengar rumor aneh.
Rumor has it
Rumornya adalah
that the coach asked Dong-seok to let Baek-du win.
pelatih meminta Dong-seok membiarkan Baek-du menang.
Did you know about it?
Kau tahu soal itu?
Gosh, what on earth is happening in this town?
Astaga, apa yang sebenarnya terjadi di kota ini?
Subtitle translation by: Sunyoung Baek
Terjemahan subtitle oleh Judith Aulia P.